Preliminary Inventory to the Sig Mickelson Papers 1950-1995
Hoover Institution Archives
- Sound recordings of people interviewed by Sig Mickelson
  - Lester, Jane, sound recording, 5 May 1982 (Box 22)
    This interview concerns a speech made by Senator Clifford Case in 1971 and legislation of that era. Lester was a Free Europe employee since 1957, assistant to presidents, 1967-82, assistant secretary of RFE/RL Inc. Cassette 11. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0003878
  - Lindsay, Franklin A., sound recording, February 1983 (Box 22)
    Cassette 56 consists of a sound recording of Sig Mickelson summarizing interviews with Franklin A. Lindsay and two others. Cassette 56. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004741
  - Lodeesen, Jon, sound recording, 22 June 1981 (Box 22)
    The interview on Cassette 13 concerns Lodeesen's biography, CIA involvement, dealing with politicians in Washington, heading the Russian service, the three waves of Russian émigrés (post-revolution, WWII-era, and modern-day), administrators at RL, anti-Semitism, problems with a long-time employee, comparing the news broadcasts of then and now, and RL during the bombing. In the interview on Cassette 16, Lodeesen discusses the differences between the Radios and how Radio Liberty functions. Topics include the domination of RFE over RL, difficulty in obtaining information for the Asian services, the tone of the Russian service, and what the listeners find pleasing and offensive. Lodeesen was a program policy executive at RL Russian Service. Cassette 13, 16, 28. Use copy reference numbers: 82074_a_0003898 and 82074_a_0004051
  - Lyon, Samuel, sound recording, 18 December 1980 (Box 22)
  - Mahoney, William, sound recording, 14-19 June 1981 (Box 22)
  - Marrero, Ernesto, sound recording, undated (Box 22)
    Marrero was a senior executive, Ministry of Communications of Spain; assigned as liaison to RLC, 1957-. Cassette 20. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004060
  - Matusevitch, Vladimir, sound recording, 2 June 1982 (Box 22)
    The interview on cassette 13 focuses on the Matusevitch's life story. He recalls how he 'escaped' from the Soviet Union into Norway, was granted asylum in Denmark, and joined the radio, eventually moving to Munich from the Copenhagen office. On cassette 30 he discusses anti-Semitism in Russia and the Soviet Union, followed by several problems within the Russian service. Matusevitch, a defector from the USSR, was Radio Liberty correspondent in Copenhagen, managing editor of the Radio Liberty Russian Service, 1973-76, and senior commentator. Cassette 13, 30. Use copy reference numbers: 82074_a_0003892 and 82074_a_0004199
  - Meyer, Cord, sound recording, 13-14 October 1981 (Box 22)
    Meyer was the CIA executive in charge of oversight of Free Europe Inc. and RLC, 1954-71. Cassette 31. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004215
  - Michalowski, Zy'gmunt, sound recording, 18 December 1980 (Box 22)
    The content of this interview is similar to that covered with Bellus and Szabados, but focuses on Poland instead of Czechoslovakia or Hungary. Among the topics covered are worker revolt over prices in Poland, process of confirming news validity, news sources, autonomy of services to add to stories from the central news room, and the influence RFE has in Poland. Michalowski was director, RFE Polish service, 1975-81. Cassette 4, 26. Use copy reference numbers: 82074_a_0003437 and 82074_a_0004089
  - Mitchell, John, F. B., Jr., sound recording, undated (Box 22)
    Mitchel drafted the articles of incorporation for American committee, 1951; served as general counsel. Cassette 25. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004082
  - Monditsch-Dreving, Victoria (Vicky Semenova), sound recording, 2 June 1982 (Box 22)
    Speaking through a male interpreter, Monditsch-Drevine describes her work at Radio Liberation/Liberty. She was Russian service staff, Radio Liberty, 1952-. Cassette 32. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004325
  - Netto, Horacio, sound recording, 2 June 1981 (Box 22)
    Netto was chief engineer, Gloria base. He joined RFE in 1951. Cassette 33. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004338
  - North, Paul, sound recording, 2 June 1981 (Box 22)
    North describes the work of the base in Portugal and how it worked with Munich and other offices. He was manager, RL base Playa de Pals, ??-1980, and manager, Portuguese operations of RFE/RL, 1980-. Cassette 33. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004338
  - Nowak, Jan, sound recording, 14 October 1981 (Box 22)
    The interview is an in depth conversation about the actions of the Polish service, particularly in the 1950s. Topics covered include, but are not limited to: a third party broadcasting code messages; the importance of having good employees; the possibility of Polish liberation in the 1950s; controversial broadcasts by the Polish service and the service's criticism of Polish officials; the role of RFE as dialog with peoples over public policy; the rivalry between the Munich and New York offices; the impact of various, notable individuals on RFE; stages of RFE's history; unions; and jamming. Nowak was director of the Polish service, RFE Munich, 1951-75. Cassette 10. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0003553
  - Orshansky, Boris, sound recording, undated (Box 22)
    Orshansky speaks about several topics: life in Russia and experiences in the Russian army, defecting to the West through the Brandenburg Gate because of what he saw and wanting to escape the dictatorship, joining Radio Liberty, divisions and internal squabbling within Radio Liberty, religion, and an assassination attempt on his life. Orhansky was a Russian army officer to 1946; first employee of Radio Liberty Russia Service. Cassette 8. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0003548
  - Ovadia, Susan, sound recording, 11 June 1981 (Box 22)
    Ovadia was news service correspondent in Paris. Cassette 34. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004340
  - Perreira, Carmen Da Costa, sound recording, 1-2 June 1981 (Box 22)
    Perreira was secretary to Raret, Lison, 1951; manager of the Lisbon office, 1975-1981. Comments on the interview are on cassette 39. Cassette 36, 39. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004570 and 82074_a_0004610
  - Petrouskienne, Lydia, sound recording, 11 June 1981 (Box 22)
    Petrouskienna was administrative manager, Paris office, RFE/RL. Cassette 34. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004340
  - Petzall, Horst, sound recording, undated (Box 22)
    Petrall (Petzall) was [?]ew director, New York office of RFE to 1975. Cassette 38. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004595
  - Pforzheimer, Walter, sound recording, 7 August 1982 (Box 22)
    Pforlheimer was legislative counsel for the CIA during the founding of Free Europe Inc. and American Committee for Liberation. Cassette 25. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004082
  - Pinto Basto, Tomas, sound recording, 1-2 June 1981 (Box 22)
    Pinto, a Portuguese industrialist, was long time chairman of RARET. Cassette 39. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004610
  - Playa de Pals staff, sound recording, 8 June 1981 (Box 22)
    Includes seven staff members: Martin Diumenge, manager, accounting staff; Fernando Friol, manager, administrative services; Alberto Gay, manager, personnel; Francisco Gullon, manager, transmitter department; Andres Llorente, manager, technical support; Rafael Moreno, chief engineer; and Antonio Reigosa, manager. Cassette 35. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004556
  - Poole, A. Russell, sound recording, 14-19 June 1981; 2 June 1982 (Box 22)
    Poole was Director of Administration, RFE/RL Munich. Cassette 19, 37. Use copy reference numbers: 82074_a_0000202 and 82074_a_0004581
  - Rahr, Gleb, sound recording, 2 June 1982 (Box 22)
    Rahr recounts his biography, family background, Russian immigrants, and his work at the NTS and Radio Liberty. Rahr was a producer of Russian historical programs at Radio Liberty Munich and a member of the NTS, 1975-. Cassette 30. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004199
  - Ralis, Max, sound recording, 10 June 1981 (Box 22)
    Ralis was organizer of RL audience research. Cassette 40. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004613
  - Rates, Nestor, sound recording, undated (Box 22)
    Rates was a member of the Romanian service (RFE) staff, Washington. Cassette 41. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004626
  - Redlich, Robert, sound recording, 14-19 June 1981 (Box 22)
    Topics include: Redlich's biography, including how he joined Radio Liberty on April Fools Day 1957; his supervisors at RL; the RL administration; transmitting bases; RL's relationship with the press; restrictions on RL; differences between RFE and RL, including, but not limited to, American citizenry's awareness of RL and lack of labor union difficulties at RL as compared to RFE; attitude of RL broadcasts over time; Redlich's public speaking about RFE/RL; and RFE/RL's relationship with the German government. Cassette 15, 19. Use copy reference numbers: 82074_a_0000202 and 82074_a_0003897
  - Rehman, Karl, sound recording, 1 October 1981 (Box 22)
    Rehman was a defector from CSSR in 1948, and was on the RFE and RFE/RL staff since 1957, primarily in policy positions, including policy executive, New York production center. Cassette 38, 42. Use copy reference numbers: 82074_a_0004595 and 82074_a_0004627
  - Ronalds, Francis F., Jr., sound recording, October 1981 (Box 22)
    Ronalds joined RL 1953, served successively as news director, correspondent, program director, vice president and executive director, Munich. Cassette 43. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004635
  - Salkazanova, Fatima, sound recording, undated (Box 22)
    Cassette 34. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004340
  - Sargeant, Howland H., sound recording, 13 May 1981; 30 September 1981; 6-11 May 1981; 12 October 1982 (Box 22)
    Sargeant was president, American Committee for Liberation (RLC), 1954-1975. Cassette 44, 45, 46, 47. Use copy reference numbers: 82074_a_0004641, 82074_a_0004643, 82074_a_0004648, and 82074_a_0004655
  - Schulz, Waldemar, sound recording, 23 June 1981 (Box 22)
    In this monologue, Schulz describes how he came to work at RFE and the union. He explains why he joined both, his duties in the union, working conditions at RFE, and how the union advocated for needed insurance and higher pay. Schulz was the head of RFE unit of German Employees Union, member of Works Council. Cassette 14. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0003893
  - Sebesta, Ludovic, sound recording, 30 September 1981 (Box 22)
    Sebesta was an adm manager, RFE/RL Czechoslovak service; member, New York production staff; head, Czechoslovak service of RFE NY. The interview begins on cassette 48 and continues on cassette 42. Cassette 42, 48. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004627 and 82074_a_0004658
  - Smith, C. Rodney, Major General, sound recording, 13-14 October 1981 (Box 22)
    Smith was vice president of Free Europe, 1959-60, and director, Radio Free Europe, 1960-67. Cassette 31. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004215
  - Sosin, Gene, sound recording, 14 April 1981; 30 September 1981; 17 August 1982 (Box 22)
    Sosin was a Radio Liberty staff member, 1961-; Radio Liberty executive from American Committee for Liberation founding; senior member, American Committee for Liberation (RLC) staff from 1961; previously a member of the Institute for Study of USSR. The interview on cassette 49 concerns the beginning years of Radio Libertation/Liberty through the 1970s, and was recorded on 14 April 1981. Cassette 25, 48, 49. Use copy reference numbers: 82074_a_0004082, 82074_a_0004658 and 82074_a_0004667
  - Sultan, Garip, sound recording, 25 June 1981 (Box 22)
    Sultan talks about his work. Aspects of the conversation focused on are issues relating to Muslims in the central Asia area, recruiting employees, and the other central Asian services of RFE/RL. The second side of the cassette is various recordings of classical/church music. Sultan is a staff member of the Tatar-Bashkir service. Cassette 6. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0003546
  - Szabados, Josef, sound recording, 24 June 1981 (Box 22)
    Mickelson interviews Josef Szabados about his life and work with the Hungarian service of Radio Free Europe. On his biographical information, Szabados explains how he left Hungary in 1949 and started working at Radio Free Europe in an economic role. He talks a bit about the Free University. The conversation quickly turns to the Hungarian service. Szabados says he learned his broadcasting skills while working at RFE, having worked in the general organization before joining a specific language service. He talks about the challenges and successes of putting together an effective organization. He says the service modifies its material to appeal to the Hungarian listeners. He describes the quality control process at the service. Szabados left Hungary, 1956; director, RFE Hungarian service, 1974-. Cassette 4. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0003437
  - Taylor, David, sound recording, 2 June 1982 (Box 22)
    Taylor was a member, Audience Research staff, RFE Munich; member, Works Council; executive of ANG unit. Cassette 22. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004074
  - Thomas, H. Gregory, sound recording, 12 May 1981; February 1983 (Box 22)
    Thomas was charter director, Free Europe Inc. He negotiated the Portuguese lease and license. Cassette 56 consists of a sound recording of Sig Mickelson summarizing interviews with Thomas and two others, February 1983. Cassette 50, 56. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004682 and 82074_a_0004741
  - Tuck, Robert, sound recording, 26 June 1981 (Box 22)
    Tuck was a long-time member of the RL program staff; member, executive director, nationalities, Russian service, NY office, etc. Cassette 51. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004689
  - Tyszkiewicz, Jan sound recording, 1 June 1982 (Box 22)
    Tyszkiewicz was a member, RFE Polish Service; producer of "The Bridge," 1981-82. Cassette 22. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004074
  - Urban, George, sound recording, 24 June 1981 (Box 22)
    After recalling Urban's biography, this interview looks at how RFE's reaction to various forms of communism and various topics informs the impact it has. The Hungarian Revolution, Czech events, what the listener heard, ecology as a broadcast topic, and CIA involvement are among the topics covered. Urban was a member of RFE Program Service based in London. Cassette 14. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0003893
  - Van Duyk, Morton, sound recording, 16 October 1981 (Box 22)
    Van Duyk was successively a member RFE news service Munich, correspondent in Brussels, and correspondent in Washington, DC. He describes the state of journalism at RFE, both when he began and during its growth into a professional news organization. He also comments on how the American press views RFE journalists. The second side of the tape contains a few CBS news broadcasts. Cassette 52. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004697
  - Walter, Ralph, sound recording, 25 June 1981; 1 June 1982 (Box 22)
    The interview on Cassette 17 concerns martial law in Poland and RFE/RL's reaction and coverage thereof, accusations about moving messages in code to organizations such as Solidarity, funding for RFE/RL (corporate funding, Fulbright, possible Western European contributions), why people work at RFE and RFE/RL, Hazelhoff (sp?) case, Powell amendment. On cassette 28, Walter discusses the independence of the radios from politicization and the staffing needs of Radio Liberty. The interview on cassette 53 concerns the change of RFE from an enthusiastic instrument for change into a professional news organization. Walter was a member of Free Europe staff from 1951; director of RFE, 1967-75; vice president of RFE/RL programs and policy, 1975-78; executive vice president, 1978-82. Cassette 17, 28, 53. Use copy reference numbers: 82074_a_0003899, 82074_a_0004191, and 82074_a_0004698
  - Washburn, Abbott, sound recording, undated (Box 22)
    Washburn was executive vice president of the Crusade for Freedom, 1950-1952, and charter member, BIB, 1974-1975. Cassette 54. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004725
  - Yurasov, Rudolf, sound recording, 13 May 1981 (Box 22)
    Yurasov was a defector from the USSR, 1946, and a member of the American Committee for Liberation (RLC) staff, 1952-. Cassette 55. Use copy reference number: 82074_a_0004740
- CBS News (Box 23-27)
- Election coverage, 1960s (Box 23-27)
- CBS News (Box 28)
- RFE/RL: Mickelson's retirement as president (Box 28)
- GAO study, 1981 (Box 28)
- Book project outline and interview notes for dictation (Box 28)
- CBS (Box 29)
- Ditchley Foundation Conference on Media and Politics, 1973 (Box 29)
- RFE/RL correspondence, 1975-1978 (Box 30)
- Mickelson book items (Box 30)
- Speeches (Box 30)
- Fiscal year budget, 1977 (Box 30)
- RFE/RL and BIB publications (Box 31)
- Matusevich libel lawsuit (Box 31)
- Mickelson memorial service (Box 31)
- Détente through Soviet Eyes, John Scott, 1974 (Box 32)
- RL VP since 1973 (Box 32)
- 10 years in Soviet Union, Time, and other publications (Box 32)
- BIB Reports (Box 32)
- RFE Audience Research Reports (Box 32)
- RFE/RL Miscellany (Box 33)
- Paul L. Heine (Box 33)
- RFE Audience Research Reports (Box 33)
- "War of the Black Heavens," Michael Nelson's draft manuscript (Box 33)